(upbeat music)
- Hello English learners,
welcome back to English.
- Hi, my name is Marco.
- And my name is Katherine, and
today we're talking about being clean.
- Yeah, we're gonna be
doing the laundry, right?
- It's a very important part
of everyone's weekly schedule.
- And not only important, but
I find it to be a little bit difficult,
because you know, like washing machine
and what clothes you should mix with what,
and you know, how much
detergent and how long,
it's such a complicated process.
- Well, let's say this.
- It might not be difficult,
but it's very easy to mess up.
- Exactly, yeah, that's the problem.
It's very easy to like
just ruin your favorite
t-shirt if you don't
do laundry correctly.
- Or all of your white
socks turn pink, for example.
- Right, so we're gonna be looking
at a lot of vocabulary and
phrases related to this topic,
and before we get
started with the dialogue,
why don't we take a look
at vocabulary preview?
- Very vocabulary preview.
Okay, so central to all
of these phrases and
words that we're gonna
be hearing is a thing,
an electric thing that
helps us wash our clothes.
- Right, a washing machine.
- All right, pretty simple, right?
So washing is a two wash,
washing, and machine.
So they go together, washing the sheet.
- Right, simple.
- So it's easy now, you
just put all your clothes
in this thing and it washes it for you.
- Boom, boom, boom, boom.
- Now, you know, a lot of people
don't like to use washing machines.
It says, hey, it doesn't really clean
the clothes as well as doing it by hand.
- Really?
- Because they most clothes get washed
pretty well with the washing machine.
But if you have those
hard to get stains or some
dirt, maybe it's good
to have a washing board.
- A washing board, yeah.
- Yeah, where you can
really scrub it yourself.
- And well, funny, you
mentioned that word stain
because it's our second word
that we're gonna preview a stain.
- All right, a stain is some
color, maybe some food
or wine or grass that you
can't remove from your clothes.
- Right.
- So it's very common,
you're having a nice dinner
and all of a sudden you
spill wine on your shirt.
So you have a wine stain.
- I hate that.
And you can also have a
stain on your carpet, right?
So if you spill some coffee on your carpet,
it's got a little circle
that's brown forever, right?
Or even some people
have stained teeth, right?
- That's right, so you
can get them turned
back white with all the
money to your dentist.
- Exactly.
So those are the two
words that we're gonna
be looking at today
in vocabulary preview.
So let's listen to our dialogue.
Let's see what's happening with
these people that are doing laundry.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, let's go through
this one more time.
I don't want any more
ruined or dyed blouses.
- I know, I know.
- Okay, so I had to separate
the colors from the whites
and put them in this strange looking
contraptions so called washing machine.
- Right, you have to
turn it on and program it,
depending on what type
of clothes you're washing.
For example, for delicates, you
should set a shorter washing cycle.
Also, be sure to use fabric softener
and this detergent when washing.
- So complicated.
Okay, what about this red wine stain?
How do I get it out?
- Since this is a white
t-shirt, you can just pour a
little bit of bleach on
it and it will do the trick.
- Cool, then I can just
throw everything in
the dryer for an hour
and it's all set, right?
- No, since you're washing
delicates and cotton,
you should set the dryer's
medium heat and for 20 minutes.
- You know what?
I'll just have everything dry cleaned.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, so we've got someone who is
maybe doing the laundry for the first time
and he's not really
understanding the instructions.
- Well, that's the thing I tell you.
It's a little bit difficult and
well, it's very tedious at times
to try and do laundry like this.
- Well, the first thing it's
maybe tedious about it is that
you have to really worry
about what colors go together.
- Right, so let's take
a look at those words
that we're related to doing
laundry now in language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
Okay, the first word we
have is actually related
to a joke we made
earlier about pink socks.
So if you change the color
of something, you're dying it.
- Okay, die.
So it's pronounced exactly the same way as,
you know, to die to not live anymore, die.
But it's spelled differently.
- D-Y-E.
- Okay, so it can be
a verb or an adjective.
- Or now.
- So something that you put on clothes
to change the color is called a die.
- A die.
- But to do this, to change
the color of some clothes
is to die the clothes.
- Mm-hmm.
- So that's maybe what
happens when you wash
a red t-shirt with
all your white t-shirt.
- Then you have dyed shirts,
you have pink shirts and no.
- And also women when they go to
the beauty so long they die their hair.
- Exactly, so that means you
change the color of your hair.
It means it's a long term change.
It's not short, it's not like one day.
- Right.
- It means probably for a long time.
So that's the correct word to die.
Very different, maybe some
people say to paint, which you
know, we understand, but the
correct form would be to die.
- And next we have a word that
describes a certain kind of clothing.
We're not talking about pants or socks.
We're talking about delicates.
- Delicates.
So now this adjective, delicate,
which means it's very-- - Easy to break.
- Fragile, right? - Yeah.
- But this is a noun, delicates.
- Right, so you think of
something that's easy to
break or to ruin, maybe
you think of underwear.
You know, underwear is something you wear.
Under your clothing,
and so it's generally
not as strong as a
shirt or a pair of jeans.
And so we call these in English, delicates.
- Very good.
So you have to be careful
when you're washing
your delicates because
it's happened to me before.
You like put them in with all the clothes
and then you have stretched
out boxers or something like that.
- Yeah, so that's why many women,
I know, washed delicates by hand.
So you separate the
clothes from the delicates.
- Very good.
And now if you're washing
delicates or washing towels
or t-shirts, it's always a good
idea to use fabric softener.
- All right, fabric softener,
what are these two words?
One of them you understand
already, maybe it's soft softener.
- So it makes it soft.
- Yeah, it's something that
makes something softer.
We've got fabric softeners.
That's something that makes
the clothes that you wash softer.
- So fabric is any type of material, right?
Like a textile.
- Yeah, it could be cotton or silk.
- Or nylon, linen.
So these are all kinds of fabrics.
- So you pour a little
bit of this in your washing
machine and your clothes
come out really nice and soft.
It feels nice just talking about it.
- All right, and we'll
also to wash your clothes
to actually make them
clean, you use detergent.
- Right, so many people might
want to say the words soap
because soap is what
we use to wash our hands
and our dishes, but
here we have detergent.
So this is a special soap for your clothes.
- Right, laundry detergent.
- Yeah, you could just say laundry
detergent or simply detergent.
And now in order to remove
those nasty stains that maybe
are very hard, you would
use a chemical called bleach.
- All right, so bleach is
the dangerous chemical
because it smells very strong.
- Right.
- And it can change the color
of your clothes to white or yellow.
So we usually only use
bleach with white clothes.
I actually had a friend who changed the
color of his hair to white using bleach.
He put bleach on his head and
on his hair and it just turned white.
- Oh wow, so many people do that
because they want to go
from dark colors to light colors.
- And in that case, you wouldn't say,
you could say that he dyed his hair white,
but usually you would
say he bleached his hair.
- It's so we understand
that it turned white.
- Exactly.
So those five words we just
looked at in language takeaway,
they're important, they're
related to doing laundry.
So before we move on, let's listen to our
dialogue again, but a little bit slower.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, let's go through
this one more time.
I don't want any more
ruined or dyed blouses.
- I know, I know.
- Okay, so I have to separate
the colors from the whites
and put them in this strange looking
contraption so-called washing machine.
- Right, you have to
turn it on and program it
depending on what type
of clothes you are washing.
For example, for delicates, you
should set a shorter washing cycle.
Also, be sure to use fabric softener
and this detergent when washing.
- So complicated.
- Okay, what about this red wine stain?
How do I get it out?
- Since this is a white
t-shirt, you can just pour a
little bit of bleach on
it and it will do the trick.
- Cool, then I can just
throw everything in
the dryer for an hour
and it's all set, right?
- No, since you are
washing delicates and cotton,
you should set the dryer to
medium heat and for 20 minutes.
- You know what?
I'll just have everything dry clean.
(upbeat music)
- So here at English Pub, we'd
like to also provide you listeners
with some phrases that allow
you to increase your fluencies.
That means sound more
like a native English speaker.
And so today let's check out
these phrases in fluency builder.
- Fluency builder.
- All right, so on fluency builder,
we're gonna be looking at
four words or four phrases.
So the first one was really easy.
When she was telling the guy or
instructing him how to do the laundry,
she said, "Let's go
through this one more time.
" - Go through what?
The wall?
- No, so it's not actually to go
through an object like to pass.
So it's let's repeat or
let's rehearse again.
- Okay, so normally we say this when there
are many different steps to do something.
So let's go through this again.
When you leave work, you go home,
you unlock the door, you open the door,
and then so it means
that there's a process.
There are many steps.
So let's go through this
again as a way for us to say,
let's think about and discuss this process.
- Very good.
So we also use it maybe
when we're studying.
So let's go through this
subject one more time.
- When we go through
chapter five again, - Exactly.
So you would reread a chapter five.
- All right, so why don't we listen to
a couple of more examples of
how we could use go through?
- Example one.
I wanna go through chapter five again
before the exam tomorrow.
- Example two.
- David, do you have time this afternoon
to go over the details of this new project?
- Example three.
I went through my contract and it says that
I am entitled to 15 vacation days a year.
- Now this next phrase is very common
when we're using sarcasm
when we're trying to make jokes.
So we say so called, right?
So she said this so called contraption.
- It's like she doubts that
it's really a washing machine.
So I could say her so called
boyfriend wants to go out tonight.
So I say that because he
doesn't really act like a boyfriend.
So you're being sarcastic.
It's a very good way and easy
way of demonstrating sarcasm.
- Yeah, actually in the 1990s in America,
there was a very famous TV
show called My So Called Life.
And so this is my so called life.
It's almost like, it's not really
like I have any control over it.
- Yeah, or I don't really have a
life because it's kind of boring.
- Yeah, so my so called life, not bragging.
It's a joke.
- So you can say it my so called friends,
my so called job, basically, you
can almost be sarcastic with anything.
- Yeah, but be careful that
you know that it's a joke
because if you're trying to be serious,
you might make some people angry.
- Right.
And now well, she was
explaining the whole process
of how to do it and when
she recommended using
bleach, she said that
should do the trick.
- Trick, so dogs do tricks, right?
- Right, but to do the trick, right?
What is that different meaning?
All right, so she's
saying this should work.
This should fix your problem.
So that should do the trick.
- So Marco, I've been
having this itch on my foot
and I just can't, I can't seem just
to figure out what to do with it.
Do you have any suggestions?
- Yeah, you should maybe just put some
ointment on it and that should do the trick.
- All right, cool, thanks
for the suggestion.
- Yeah, so very easy is just a way of
saying that should solve your problem.
- All right, great.
So that should do the
trick or it will do the trick.
- Mm-hmm, and what we
have one last phrase, all set.
- All set, so this is another phrase
that has two words that always go together
to mean, well, we're finished, we're done.
- Everything is ready.
- We're all set to go on vacation.
So my bags are packed, I have
my passports, we are all set.
- Or after a meeting, you
can say, are we all set here?
That means are we
finished, is it time to leave?
- Very good, so we are almost all set.
Let's listen to this
dialogue one last time.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, let's go through
this one more time.
I don't want any more
ruined or dyed blouses.
- I know, I know.
- Okay, so I have to separate
the colors from the whites
and put them in this strange looking
contraption so-called washing machine.
- Right, you have to
turn it on and program it,
depending on what type
of clothes you're washing.
For example, for delicates, you
should set a shorter washing cycle.
Also, be sure to use fabric softener
and this detergent when washing.
- So complicated.
Okay, what about this red wine stain?
How do I get it out?
- Since this is a white
t-shirt, you can just pour a
little bit of bleach on
it and it will do the trick.
- Cool, then I can just
throw everything in
the dryer for an hour
and it's all set, right?
- No, since you're washing
delicates and cotton,
you should set the dryer to
medium heat and for 20 minutes.
- You know what?
I'll just have everything dry cleaned.
(upbeat music)
- Have you ever had any laundry mishaps?
Have you ever lost a sock, dyed something?
- Have I ever.
I hate doing the laundry.
- Why?
- So much, it's time consuming.
It takes a lot of time
and I just have no
patience and so normally
when I was in college
I would take all of my laundry in a
bag and I'd throw in the washing machine
and I'd put it on cold, you
know, because cold water, it's
okay for all colors but hot
water makes the colors bleed.
I took out the clothes
and put them in the dryer
and afterwards I saw all my
clothes were clean except for
my three sweaters, which
were small enough for babies.
- Oh, you shrunk it.
- Yeah, I shrunk three brand new sweaters.
- Oh, yeah.
- That's too bad.
- The problem that I
have when doing laundry
is that I forget that I
started doing laundry
so all of a sudden, you
know, I'm doing laundry
in the morning and then
the clothes are washed
but they're still in the washing
machine and I remember like the next day.
So then the clothes
are like kind of smelling
like kind of humid 'cause they're moldy.
- Yeah, so I have to re-wash
them and it's just like a pain.
Yeah, but doing laundry
is sometimes so time
consuming but let us
know what you think.
Do you like doing laundry
or have you ever lost a sock?
- I think everyone has lost a sock
or something in the washing, right?
- I think there is a secret
home for socks somewhere.
- It's so weird.
- Maybe it's an Australia or something.
- So come to our website, englishpot.com.
Give us all your feedback, question, comments,
or suggestions and we're always there.
- All right, hope to hear from you
soon and until next time everyone.
- Bye.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]